Guide to the Jay Haley Collection, 1957-2007 M1733
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Jay Haley Collection
1957-2007
M1733
Stanford University. Department of Special Collections and University Archives
28.0 Linear feet (55 boxes)
The Jay Haley collection, consisting of 28 linear feet and spanning from the 1950s to 2007, documents Haley’s career through correspondence, papers, book typescripts, and media materials. Among Haley’s papers documenting his multiple professional activities are his writings on: psychotherapy as a profession; teaching therapy; studies on Milton H. Erickson M. D.; the Bateson Project; marriage and family therapy; schizophrenia; his work with the Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic, and his activities as editor for the Journal Family Process. The collection also includes Haley’s fiction writings, and his training films on topics such as: strategic and family therapy, Milton H. Erickson M.D., documentation of specific cases, and trance and dance in Bali.
The collection contains paper and audio visual materials
Haley, Jay
Access to Collection
Open for research with written authorization in accordance with Special Collections and University Archives Access to Health Information of Individuals Policy, available at http://www-sul.stanford.edu/depts/spc/pubserv/access_to_health_policy.pdf. Also case studies in series 3.3 and 8.5 are closed and will be available one hundred years from the date of creation. Non-digital audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy. For additional information see Stanford University, Special Collections and University Archives, Duplication Services.
Collection Outline
The Jay Haley Collection is organized in 8 series:
Series 1. Correspondence is Subdivided 3 Subseries: Subseries 1.1 Contributors for the journal Family Process; Subseries 1.2 Subscriptions for the journal Family Process; Subseries 1.3 Personal.
Series 2. Haley’s Writings is Subdivided 15 Subseries: Subseries 2.1 Psychotherapy as a profession; Subseries 2.2 Teaching therapy; Subseries 2.2.5 Strategic (directive) therapy; Subseries 2.3 Milton H. Erickson; Subseries 2.4 Hypnosis; Subseries 2.5 Gregory Bateson, the Bateson Project, paradoxes; Subseries 2.6 Marriage/family therapy; Subseries 2.7 Schizophrenia; Subseries 2.8 Sexual abuse; Subseries 2.9 Hierarchies, power tactics; Subseries 2.10 Feminism; Subseries 2.11 Cross-cultural experiments; race studies; Subseries 2.12 Media: violence, social themes and group structure; Subseries 2.13 Haley on peers’ writings; Subseries 2.14 General topics journalism, fiction, and miscellaneous; Subseries 2.15 Collection of Haley’s books in various languages.
Series 3. Haley’s Work is Subdivided in 6 Subseries: Subseries 3.1 Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic; Subseries 3.2 Conferences, workshops, seminars, meetings: organizing materials, notes, papers; Subseries 3.3 Restricted medical records: case studies, notes, transcriptions of sessions, problem codes; Subseries 3.4 Training films, interviews: film scripts, audio transcriptions, summaries, correspondence, grant proposals, agreements; Subseries 3.5 Therapists, trainees, and programs: questionnaires, statistics; Subseries 3.6 Bibliographies.
Series 4. Haley’s Legal/Personal Documents is Subdivided in 5 Subseries: Subseries 4.1 Contracts, accreditations, agreements, releases, copyright; Subseries 4.2 Personal documents: school transcripts, diplomas, CV; Subseries 4.3 Collection of quotes of Haley’s and other people; Subseries 4.4 Awards, tributes, festschriften; Subseries 4.5 Obituaries.
Series 5. Milton H. Erickson M.D. is Subdivided in 7 Subseries: Subseries 5.1 Erickson’s writings; Subseries 5.2 Erickson’s cases; Subseries 5.3 Transcripts of conversations with Erickson; Subseries 5.4 Correspondence; Subseries 5.5 Bibliographies; Subseries 5.6 On Erickson and his work; Subseries 5.7 Miscellaneous.
Series 6. Other Authors' Writings is Subdivided in 4 Subseries: Subseries 6.1 On Jay Haley: general articles and reviews of his books, articles, and films; Subseries 6.2 Typescripts (unknown if published); Subseries 6.3 Published papers, clippings; Subseries 6.4 Fiction.
Series 7. Family Process Journals, Jay Haley ed.
Series 8. Media is Subdivided in 4 Subseries: Subseries 8.1 Audio: Reel to reel and cassette tapes; Subseries 8.2 Audio: Compact discs; Subseries 8.3 Video cassettes; Subseries 8.4 Digital video discs; Subseries 8.5 Restricted Media.
Background
Jay Haley (1923-2007) was born in an oil town in Wyoming. He was a pioneer in family therapy, and his work traces its birth and development during half a century. He was a founder and first editor of Family Process, the first journal in family therapy. Haley was pivotal in creating psychotherapy's major paradigm shift from insightful, long-term therapy, to a brief, family-based and problem-focused strategic therapy. Haley argued for training therapists through live supervision, giving them the necessary tools for problem solving through an active thoughtfully planned strategy. He pioneered the recording of therapy sessions, and created many training films.
Jay Haley held degrees from UCLA, U.C. Berkeley and Stanford University. While at Stanford he met Gregory Bateson and as a young member of the Gregory Bateson Research Project, he participated in the early research in family therapy and schizophrenia. His work on leading medical hypnotist Dr. Milton H. Erickson in Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton Erickson M.D. (1973), influenced many people to become therapists. He elaborated and codified a brief strategic family therapy approach, which grew out of Erickson's work, and departed in many significant ways from the more traditional approach to therapy. It emphasized the present not the past, a positive unconscious not a negative unconscious, a focus on action rather than developing insight, and emphasizing the skills needed to solve problems rather than diagnosis.
In the mid 1960's Jay Haley joined Salvador Minuchin and Braulio Montalvo at the Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic as Director of Family Therapy Research for ten years. They received a grant to train paraprofessionals in the community (poor African Americans and Latinos). This innovative training and live supervision is published in Problem-Solving Therapy, a text for learning therapeutic skills. Haley also served as Clinical Associate Professor at the University of Pennsylvania. He co-founded The Family Therapy Institute of Washington, DC, and served as Professor of Clinical Psychiatry at Howard University, and at the University of Maryland, where he continued his pioneering work in training therapists from around the world in directive family therapy. In the early 1990's he returned to California joined the faculty of Alliant International University, continued making training films, writing, and lecturing until his death in 2007. His contributions have been published in 21 books, more than 100 papers, which have been translated into 15 languages, and many therapy films.
Scope and Content
The Jay Haley collection contains materials spanning from the 1950s to 2007. It documents Haley’s career through correspondence, papers, book typescripts, and media materials. Among Haley’s papers documenting his multiple professional activities are his writings on: psychotherapy as a profession; teaching therapy; studies on Milton H. Erickson M. D.; the Bateson Project; marriage and family therapy; schizophrenia; his work with the Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic, and his activities as editor for the Journal Family Process. The collection also includes Haley’s fiction writings, and his training films on topics such as: strategic and family therapy, Milton H. Erickson M.D., documentation of specific cases, and trance and dance in Bali.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Madeleine Richeport-Haley, 2009. Accession 2009-287.
Bateson, Gregory, 1904-1980; Erickson, Milton H.; Jackson, Don D. (Don De Avila), 1920-1968; Minuchin, Salvador; Montalvo, Braulio; Richeport-Haley, Madeleine; Watts, Alan, 1915-1973; Weakland, John H.; Bateson Project; Brief psychotherapy; Double bind (Psychology); Family Life Cycle; Family therapy; Family therapy experiments; Hypnosis and altered states of consciousness; Psychotherapy; Schizophrenia; Strategic (Directive) Therapy; Substance abuse; Teaching "non-therapists"
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1957-2004
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence is arranged chronologically with letters to and from Haley together. It consists mainly of invitations to participate in conferences, symposia, workshops, and all kinds of public speaking events. In particular from the late 1970s there is a constant stream of invitations for speaking engagements all over the world. There are also petitions to review peers’ writings; requests for information on professional matters, especially on training; communications on the publications of Haley’s books and articles, and their multiple translations into Japanese, Spanish, Italian, German, French, etc. From 1977 on the vast majority of the letters are to Haley and only a few are by him.
  - Subseries 1.1 Contributors for Journal Family Process, 1959-1967; Ackerman, Nathan W. (Nathan Ward), 1908-1971; Jackson, Don D. (Don De Avila), 1920-1968
    In 1962, in collaboration with Don D. Jackson and Nathan Ackerman, Haley founded the journal Family Process. He was the editor for the first decade. The correspondence from 1959 through 1967, which is arranged chronologically, deals with letters of submissions to Family Process, and the corresponding acceptance or rejection letters.
    - 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 1.2 Subscriptions for Journal Family Process, 1964-1966
    The letters in this subseries deal with Family Process subscription requests and orders of back issues.
    - 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 1.3 Personal, 1957-2004
    Haley's personal letters make up the largest subseries in the correspondence series. Haley's chronological organization of the letters was retained. The content of the letters deal with Haley's writings, publications, teaching, conferences, and Haley's requesting permission to publish portions or complete articles of colleagues or vice versa.
    - 1957-1963, Bateson, Gregory, 1904-1980; Erickson, Milton H.; Watts, Alan, 1915-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      These early letters deal with Haley's book Strategies of Psychotherapy (1963) and also writings on schizophrenia and the double bind. Some of the correspondents include: Gregory Bateson, Allan Watts, and Milton H. Erickson M. D.
    - Bernard E. Gorton, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Letters between Jay Haley, Andre Weitzenhoffer, and Bernard E. Gorton. Philadelphia Conference (1958) and San Francisco Seminar (1959) on Milton H. Erickson's theories on hypnosis, psychotherapy and communications; on collaborating on a Festschrift for Erickson's 60th birthday (1961); discussion on an Erickson book published in 1961 The practical application of medical and dental hypnosis. The book Advanced Techniques of Hypnosis and Therapy, the Selected Papers of Milton Erickson M.D. edited by Haley was dedicated to Bernard E. Gorton.
    - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      On Haley joining the Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic as director of Family Research (1967); on the publication of Haley's book Techniques of Family Therapy; relocation to Philadelphia; on Richard Rabkin becoming the new editor for the Family Process journal book review section (Nov. 67); invitations for speaking engagements and for writing articles; requests for reprints of Haley's articles, such as "The Art of Being a Schizophrenic" (1966). Some of the correspondents include: Salvador Minuchin, Antonio J. Ferreira, John Weakland, Frank Pittman, Richard Rabkin, and Don D. Jackson.
    - 1968 Jan. - June (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Comments on articles submitted to Family Process journal; Haley's writing for the journal Voices. The Art and Science of Psychotherapy, "The Amiable Hippie,"(1968); on the publication of the book Advanced Techniques of Hypnosis and Therapy: Selected papers of Milton H. Erickson, M.D.Jay Haley, editor; on the death of Don D. Jackson; final feedback tabulation for the journal Voices. Some of the correspondents include: Milton H. Erickson, Gregory Bateson, and Nathan W. Ackerman.
    - 1968 July - Dec. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Discussion on the Gilles de la Tourette's Syndrome; planning for the Don Jackson Memorial Conference for February 1969 (audio material of conference proceedings, see under Media); reception of Haley's article "The Amiable Hippie"; criticism of Haley's article "The Mystery of Child Therapy"; self-disclosure questionnaire findings of couples group therapy of the Mental Research Institute. Some of the correspondents include: A.J.M. Morison, Milton H. Erickson, John M. Shlien, Alan Watts, Eveoleen N. Rexford, Arthur M. Bodin, and Murray Bowen.
    - 1969 Jan. - June (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Planning the Don D. Jackson Memorial Conference; reception of Haley's article "The Amiable Hippie"; response to Haley's book Strategies of Psychotherapy, (1963); Recommendation for Haley to become an Associate Professor at the University of Pennsylvania's Dept. of Psychiatry; Some of the correspondents include: Carlos E. Sluzki, Salvador Minuchin, Norman L. Paul, H.L. Ansbacher, Murray Bowen.
    - 1969 July - Dec. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Other Finding Aids note
      Submission of Haley's paper "The Mystery of Learning"; Haley's retirement as editor of Family Process journal; response to Haley's article, "The Art of Being a Failure as a Therapist" (July, 1969); invitation to the First Argentine Congress of Psychopathology of the Family Group; Haley's comments on the "Approaches to Family Therapy" (drawn from the GAP report); on Haley's article "The Amiable Hippie"; on the MRI bibliography covering 1950 to1970 with Ira Glick; Some of the correspondents include: S.J. Marks, John E. Bell, Donald A. Molde, Carlos E. Sluzki, Alan Watts, Jason Aronson, Edward J. Callahan
    - 1970 Jan. - June (Box 3, Folder 4)
      On Haley's clinical writings for Science House publishers, includes a list of relevant works; Milton H. Erickson becoming honorable member of the Sociedad Mexicana de Medicina Psicosomatica e Hipnosis Clinica, also Honorary vice president for Life of the British Society of Medical and Dental Hypnosis of England, and vice President of the International Congress in Spain; on Haley training the poor in Philadelphia to become family therapists; panel for the APA May meeting; on the differences and similarities between group therapy and family therapy; Haley's letter to the Local Draft Board on behalf of Dr. Howard Baker; severing relations with Family Process journal; on the dispute of republishing papers submitted to Family Process journal; early planning stages of Haley's book Changing Families: A Family Therapy Reader; finishing Advanced Techniques of Hypnosis and Therapy; Selected Papers of Milton H. Erickson, M. D.; Some of the correspondents include: Jason Aronson, Milton H. Erickson, Donald A. Bloch, Ira D. Glick, Richard J. Moore, Salvador Minuchin, Gerald H. Zuk, Nathan W. Ackerman, John E. Bell.
    - 1970 July - Dec. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      On the family therapy bibliography and research (1950-1970) offered to Science House publishers; publishing a history on the Bateson Project from 1961; Tourette Syndrome; on the Erickson research fund at MRI; Haley's disapproval of questionnaires for studying families; family therapy course offered at the Institute of the Pennsylvania Hospital; Haley's and Bateson's discussion on power; on publishing Haley's book Changing Families: A Family Therapy Reader; on Lynn Hoffman's article "Beyond Homeostasis"; members of the Philadelphia black community trained as family therapists; exchanges with Erickson on Haley's wrapping up Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson, M.D. Some of the correspondents include: Gregory Bateson, Carlos Sluzki, Warren M. Brodey, F. S. Abuzzahab, John Weakland, Carolyn L. Attneave, Milton H. Erickson, and Lynn Hoffman.
    - 1971 Jan. - June (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Feedback on Haley’s manuscript Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson, M.D. by Lynn Hoffman and John H. Weakland; discussion on the Erickson book with Erickson; evaluating the possibility of creating a film documenting Erickson’s work; renewal of grant at the Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic to continue training poor people to be family therapists. Some of the correspondents include: Gregory Bateson, Carlos Sluzki, Lynn Hoffman, Milton H. Erickson, John H.Weakland, Howard Head, and Porfirio J. Miranda.
    - 1971 July - Dec. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Feedback on Haley’s article “Communication and Therapy”; offer of appointment as Associate Professor of Family Study in Psychiatry at University of Pennsylvania; invitation for Haley to be a visiting lecturer at Swarthmore College; critical reaction to Haley’s article “The Art of Being a Failure as a Therapist”; appointment as Psychology Consultant at the Veterans Administration in Palo Alto, CA; Haley’s observations on his family therapy training for poor African Americans, in particular the connection between a social organization and the cognition of its members. Some of the correspondents include: Carl A. Whitaker, Milton H. Erickson, Kenneth J. Gergen, Harvey Barten, C. Peter Rosenbaum, and Gregory Bateson.
    - 1972 Jan. - June (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Festschrift for Gregory Bateson; Haley’s report to S. Minuchin on the Phildelphia Child Guidance Clinic: the use of film for training, the possibility of creating a training institute for family therapists; invitation to record a discussion on the various methods and techniques of family therapy with Dr. Murray Bowen from the Council for Interdisciplinary Communication in Medicine. Some of the correspondents include: Salvador Minuchin.
    - 1972 July - Dec. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Discussion on the title of Erickson’s and Rossi’s book The February Man; Erickson’s description of the case in The February Man; Erickson’s description of a hypnosis session for a lecture at the Boston State Hospital; unusual Erickson cases to be considered for Haley’s book, Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson, M.D.; on the Japanese translation of Strategies of Psychotherapy; Haley’s advice on how to publish a successful professional journal; Haley’s ideas on couples' therapy, see letter to Arthur Raske. Some of the correspondents include: Milton H. Erickson, Noboru Takaishi, Martin G. Blinder, and Arthur Raske.
    - 1973 Jan. - May (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Haley’s brief account on the method of keeping a running tabulation for his study on treating families, see letter to Ruth Rachlis; missing out on having a preface by Margaret Mead in Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson, M.D.; on the Italian translation of Strategies of Psychotherapy; behavior modifier therapy vs. directives, and the triad of the teenage mother, baby, and grandmother, see letter to John B. Reid; reception on Haley’s book Uncommon Therapy: The Psychiatric Techniques of Milton H. Erickson, M.D.; Haley’s return interest to schizophrenia, particularly in adolescents. Some of the correspondents include: Ruth Rachlis, John Weakland, Annalisa Marzot, John B. Reid, Elizabeth Erickson, Milton H. Erickson, Kay F. Thompson, and Loren R. Mosher.
    - 1973 June - Dec. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      On treating schizophrenia, see letter to Loren R. Mosher; discussion with Carlos Sluzki on Haley’s double bind paper; on the death of Jerry Ford and Rae Weiner. Some of the correspondents include: Loren R. Mosher, Lynn Hoffman, and Carlos Sluzki.
    - 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      The letters in this folder are mainly to Haley and responses are missing with a few exceptions. This is the year that Haley resigned from the Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic. The most important topics discussed are: Dr. J. J. Sigal on long-term follow up of therapy cases; J.J. Sigal’s and Waldo Presser’s project on standardizing means of comparing different approaches to family therapy; German translations/editions of Haley’s books and articles; Some of the correspondents include: Sigal, J. J., and Karl Herbert Mandel.
    - 1977 Jan. - Aug. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      “Beyond the Double Bind” Conference; Haley’s training film Coming Home from the Mental Hospital in Sweden; Haley’s promotion to Clinical Professor of Psychiatry at Howard University in Washington D.C.; Haley training people with live supervision at the Washington D.C. Family Therapy Institute, see letter to Richard Rabkin; Sydney Tovatt’s response to Haley’s opinion of keeping schizophrenics at home with their families; Haley corrects Richard Rabkin on the theory of counterwill and the double bind. Some of the correspondents include: Milton M. Berger, Sydney Tovatt, and Richard Rabkin.
    - 1977 Sept. - Dec. (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Declining Richard Rabkin’s invitation to teach strategic therapy in New York due to ideological differences; Haley recounts the history of the founding of the journal Family Therapy, see letter to John Weakland; Haley’s suggestions for David Lipset’s book on Gregory Bateson; Some of the correspondents include: Richard Rabkin, John Weakland, Ira D. Glick, and Theo Compernolle.
    - 1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Consists only of one letter by Paul Watzlawick from the Mental Research Institute on the Fourth Don D. Jackson Memorial Conference and 20th Anniversary of MRI.
    - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      On the Fourth Don D. Jackson Memorial Conference and 20th Anniversary of MRI; Haley offers feedback to Thomas C. Todd’s and M. Duncan Stanton’s manuscript, The Family Therapy of Drug Abuse and Addiction; discussion of Haley’s “Heroin My Baby: A Clinical Study,” a chapter of the manuscript Leaving Home. Some of the correspondents include: Theo Compernolle, Jules Riskin, Paul Watzlawick, Thomas C. Todd, and M. Duncan Stanton.
    - 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      M. Duncan Stanton’s request to reprint Haley’s “Heroin My Baby: A Clinical Study,” in his and Thomas C. Todd’s book: The Family Therapy of Drug Abuse and Addiction; Haley refutes the idea that the cause of schizophrenia is organic and comments on the propensity of anti-psychotic drugs to cause irreversible neurological damage, see letter to Albert M. Honig; Reception of Haley’s book Leaving Home: The Therapy of Disturbed Young People; James W. Ingersoll recounts Haley’s deep and defining professional and personal impact on him. Some of the correspondents include: Albert M. Honig, M. Duncan Stanton, Rosmarie Welter, and James W. Ingersoll.
    - 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1984 - 1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Consists only of two letters to Haley by Mary Jane Eimer, and Howard A. Liddle
    - 1987 Jan. - Oct. (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Planning for Haley’s seminars in Tokyo and Osaka; other international invitations to conferences. Some of the correspondents include: Jeffrey K. Zeig and Keiichi Miyata.
    - 1987 Nov. - Dec. (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Haley’s response to Barbara Peeks’ paper “Strategies for Solving Children’s Problems Understood as Behavioral Metaphors”; Planning for Haley’s seminars in Tokyo and Osaka. Some of the correspondents include: Barbara Peeks and Noriyuki Fujii.
    - 1988 Jan. - April (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Haley’s criticism of the article “Management rather than Cure, the Goal with Schizophrenia,” by Kimberly A. Tilley published in Family Therapy News, and reception of Haley’s published comments. Some of the correspondents include: Elizabeth Erickson and Bruce S. Neben.